So earlier this year,
وهكذا في وقتٍ سابق من هذا العام،
I was informed that I would be doing a TED Talk.
تم إعلامي بأنني سأقدمُ محادثة TED.
So I was excited, then I panicked,
لذلك، كنتُ متحمسة، ثم شعرتُ بالذعر،
then I was excited, then I panicked,
وثم تحمستُ، وبعد ذلك شعرتُ بالذعر،
and in between the excitement and the panicking,
وبين الحماس والذعر،
I started to do my research,
بدأتُ أقوم ببحثي،
and my research primarily consisted of Googling how to give a great TED Talk.
وكان بحثي في محرك غوغل يدور أساساً حول كيفية تقديم محادثة TED رائعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And interspersed with that,
وتخلل ذلك،
I was Googling Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie.
البحث عن الروائية النيجيرية "تشيماماندا نجوزي أديتشي".
How many of you know who that is?
كم منكم يعلمُ من هذه الشخصية؟
(Cheers)
(هتاف)
So I was Googling her because I always Google her
كنتُ أبحثُ عنها لأنني دوماً أبحث عنها
because I'm just a fan,
لأنني من معجبيها،
but also because she always has important and interesting things to say.
ولكن أيضًا لأنه لديها دائمًا أمورًا مهمه ومثيرة للاهتمام لتقولها.
And the combination of those searches
وجمع هذه الأبحاث
kept leading me to her talk
التي قادتني إلى محادثتها
on the dangers of a single story,
حول مخاطر القصة الأحادية،
on what happens when we have a solitary lens
بشأن ما يحدث عندما يكون لدينا عدسة مفردة
through which to understand certain groups of people,
التي يمكنُ من خلالها فهم مجموعات محددة من الناس،
and it is the perfect talk.
وهذه هي المحادثة المثالية.
It's the talk that I would have given if I had been famous first.
وهذه المحادثة التي أرغبُ في تقديمها إذا كان لدي الشهرة أولًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, and you know, like, she's African and I'm African,
كما تعلمون وتعلمون، مثلما هي أفريقية، أنا أفريقية،
and she's a feminist and I'm a feminist,
وهي ناشطة نسائية وأنا ناشطة نسائية،
and she's a storyteller and I'm a storyteller,
وهي روائية وأنا روائية،
so I really felt like it's my talk.
شعرتُ أنه كلامي حقًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I decided that I was going to learn how to code,
لذلك قررتُ بأنني سأتعلمُ كيفية التشفير،
and then I was going to hack the internet
وثم قررتُ اختراق الإنترنت
and I would take down all the copies of that talk that existed,
وتحميل كل النسخ لتلك المحادثة القائمة،
and then I would memorize it,
وثم حفظها،
and then I would come here and deliver it as if it was my own speech.
والقدوم هنا لتقديمها على أساس أنها خطابي الخاص.
So that plan was going really well, except the coding part,
كانت ستسيرُ الخطة على ما يرام، عدا جزء التشفير،
and then one morning a few months ago,
وثم في صباح أحد الأيام قبل بضعة أشهر،
I woke up
استيقطتُ
to the news that the wife of a certain presidential candidate
على أنباء أن زوجة مرشح رئاسي معين
had given a speech that --
قد ألقت خطابًا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
that sounded eerily like a speech given by one of my other faves,
بدا وبشكل مخيف وكأنه مثل خطاب ألقي من قبل إحدى المفضلات لدي،
Michelle Obama.
"ميشيل أوباما"،
(Cheers)
(هتاف)
And so I decided that I should probably write my own TED Talk,
ولهذا، قررتُ أنه ربما ينبغى علي كتابة محادثتي الخاصة لـ TED،
and so that is what I am here to do.
وهذا هو ما سأقوم به هنا.
I'm here to talk about my own observations about storytelling.
أنا هنا للحديث عن ملاحظاتي الخاصة حول رواية القصص.
I want to talk to you about the power of stories, of course,
أرغبُ في الحديث إليكم عن قوة القصص بالطبع،
but I also want to talk about their limitations,
ولكن أريدُ أيضًا الحديث عن حدودها،
particularly for those of us who are interested in social justice.
خاصةً من أجل هؤلاء الذين هم مهتمون بالعدالة الاجتماعية.
So since Adichie gave that talk seven years ago,
لهذا، منذُ أن ألقت "أديتشي" محادثتها قبل سبع سنوات،
there has been a boom in storytelling.
أصبح هنالك الآن طفرة في رواية القصص.
Stories are everywhere,
توجد القصص في كل مكان،
and if there was a danger in the telling of one tired old tale,
وإذا كان هناك خطر في سرد إحدى الحكايات القديمة البالية المملة،
then I think there has got to be lots to celebrate about the flourishing
بالتالي، أعتقدُ أنه يوجد هناك الكثير للاحتفال حول ازدهار
of so many stories and so many voices.
العديد من القصص والأصوات الكثيرة جدًا.
Stories are the antidote to bias.
فالقصص هي كمضاد السُم بالنسبة إلى الانحياز،
In fact, today, if you are middle class and connected via the internet,
في الواقع، اليوم، إذا كنتم من الطبقة العاملة وتواصلتم عبر الإنترنت،
you can download stories at the touch of a button
فيمكنكم تحميل القصص في لمسة زر واحدة
or the swipe of a screen.
أو تمرير سريع للشاشة.
You can listen to a podcast
يمكنكم سماع البث الصوتي
about what it's like to grow up Dalit in Kolkata.
حول ما يبدو عليه الترعرع في الطبقة المنبوذة في كلكتا/الهند.
You can hear an indigenous man in Australia
يمكنكم سماع رجل من السكان الأصليين في استراليا
talk about the trials and triumphs of raising his children in dignity
يتحدثُ عن المحاولات والانتصارات لتربية أولاده في كرامة
and in pride.
وفخر وكبرياء.
Stories make us fall in love.
تجعلنا القصص نقعُ في الحب.
They heal rifts and they bridge divides.
إنها تسدّ التصدعات وتقلل الفجوات والاختلافات.
Stories can even make it easier for us
حتى يمكنُ للقصص تسهيل الأمور لنا
to talk about the deaths of people in our societies
للحديث عن تغييب الموت للناس في مجتمعاتنا
who don't matter, because they make us care.
من لا يهتمُ بذلك. بسبب أنها تجعلنا نهتم.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
I'm not so sure,
لستُ متأكدة من ذلك،
and I actually work for a place called the Centre for Stories.
وفي الحقيقة أنا أعمل في مكانْ يدعى "مركز الروايات".
And my job is to help to tell stories
وعملي هو مساعدة الآخرين على سرد القصص
that challenge mainstream narratives about what it means to be black
التي تتحدى الروايات السائدة حول ما يعنيه أن تكون من ذوي البشرة السوداء
or a Muslim or a refugee or any of those other categories
أو مسلم أو لاجىء أو أي أحد من تلك التصنيفات الاخرى
that we talk about all the time.
التي نتحدثُ عنها طوال الوقت.
But I come to this work
لكنني جئتُ لهذا العمل
after a long history as a social justice activist,
بعد تاريخ طويل كناشطة من أجل العدالة الاجتماعية
and so I'm really interested in the ways
ولذلك أنا متحمسة حقًا في الوسائل
that people talk about nonfiction storytelling
التي يسردُ فيها الناس القصص الواقعية
as though it's about more than entertainment,
ورغم ذلك هي عن شيء أكثر من الترفيه،
as though it's about being a catalyst for social action.
هي حول كيفية أن نكون محفزين من أجل العمل الاجتماعي.
It's not uncommon to hear people say
إنه من غير المالوف أن تسمع الناس تقول
that stories make the world a better place.
أن القصص تجعل العالم مكانًا أفضل.
Increasingly, though, I worry that even the most poignant stories,
وعلى نحو متزايد، وعلى الرغم أنني قلقة أنه حتى أكثر القصص المؤثرة،
particularly the stories about people who no one seems to care about,
ولا سيما تلك القصص حول الناس الذين يبدو أن لا أحد يهتم بهم،
can often get in the way of action towards social justice.
يمكنُ في الغالب حصولها في طريق العمل نحو العدالة الاجتماعية.
Now, this is not because storytellers mean any harm.
الآن، هذا ليس لأن الروائيين يقصدون أي نوع من الضرر.
Quite the contrary.
بل على العكس تمامًا.
Storytellers are often do-gooders like me and, I suspect, yourselves.
يقوم الروائيون في الغالب بأعمال خيرية مثلي وأتوقع مثلكم.
And the audiences of storytellers
وجمهور الروائيون
are often deeply compassionate and empathetic people.
هم في الغالب من الأشخاص الرحماء والمتعاطفين.
Still, good intentions can have unintended consequences,
مع ذلك، يمكنُ أن يكون للنوايا الحسنة عواقب غير مقصودة،
and so I want to propose that stories are not as magical as they seem.
ولذلك، أرغبُ في أن أشير إلى تلك القصص التي ليست سحرية كما تبدو،
So three -- because it's always got to be three --
لذلك فثلاثة يحصلُ أن تكون ثلاثة دومًا
three reasons why I think
أعتقدُ أن هناك ثلاثة أسباب
that stories don't necessarily make the world a better place.
أنه ليس بالضرورة أن تجعل القصص العالم مكانًا أفضل
Firstly, stories can create an illusion of solidarity.
الأول، تستطيع القصص إحداث وهم التضامن.
There is nothing like that feel-good factor you get
لا يوجد شيئًا مثل عامل الشعور الطيب الذي تحصلون عليه
from listening to a fantastic story
من سماع قصة رائعة
where you feel like you climbed that mountain, right,
حيثُ تشعرون وكأنكم تتسلقون الجبل، صحيح،
or that you befriended that death row inmate.
أو أنكم صادقتم ذلك السجين المحكوم عليه بالإعدام.
But you didn't.
لكنكم لم تفعلوا ذلك.
You haven't done anything.
لم تفعلوا أي شيء.
Listening is an important
الاستماع هو مهم
but insufficient step towards social action.
لكنه خطوة غير كافية نحو العمل الاجتماعي
Secondly, I think often we are drawn
ثانيًا، أعتقدُ غالبًا أنه تم جذبنا
towards characters and protagonists
نحو الشخصيات والأبطال
who are likable and human.
الذين هم محبوبون وبشر.
And this makes sense, of course, right?
وبالطبع هذا أمر منطقي، اليس كذلك؟
Because if you like someone, then you care about them.
لأنه إذا أحببتم شخصًا، فبالتالي أنتم تهتمون به.
But the inverse is also true.
ولكن العكس صحيح أيضًا.
If you don't like someone,
إذا لم تحبون أحدهم،
then you don't care about them.
فبالتالي فإنكم لا تهتمون به،
And if you don't care about them,
وإذا كنتم لا تهتمون به،
you don't have to see yourself as having a moral obligation
لا ينبغي عليكم أن تشعروا بوجود التزام أخلاقي
to think about the circumstances that shaped their lives.
للتفكير حول الظروف التي شكلت حياته.
I learned this lesson when I was 14 years old.
تعلمتُ هذا الدرس عندما كنتُ أبلغ 14 عامًا.
I learned that actually, you don't have to like someone
تعلمتُ أنه لا ينبغي عليكم حب شخص ما فعلًا
to recognize their wisdom,
لفهم حكمته،
and you certainly don't have to like someone
وبالتأكيد لا يجب محبة شخص
to take a stand by their side.
لتقفوا بجانبه.
So my bike was stolen
وهكذا سرقت دراجتي
while I was riding it --
عندما كنتُ أقودها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
which is possible if you're riding slowly enough, which I was.
وهذا محتمل إذا كنت تقودها ببطء شديد، وهذا ما كان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So one minute I'm cutting across this field
لدقيقة واحدة كنت أعبرُ هذا الحقل
in the Nairobi neighborhood where I grew up,
في أحد أحياء "نيروبي" حيثُ نشأت.
and it's like a very bumpy path,
وهي طريق وعرة جدًا،
and so when you're riding a bike,
ولذلك عندما تقودُ الدراجة،
you don't want to be like, you know --
لا ترغبُ أن تكون مثل، كما تعلمون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so I'm going like this, slowly pedaling,
وهكذا كنتُ أقود مثل ذلك، وأدوسُ ببطء،
and all of a sudden, I'm on the floor.
وبشكل مفاجىء، كنتُ على الأرض.
I'm on the ground, and I look up,
ونظرتُ للأعلى وأنا على الأرض،
and there's this kid peddling away in the getaway vehicle,
وكان هناك طفلًا يبيعُ بعيدًا عند بوابة مركبة،
which is my bike,
التي هي دراجتي،
and he's about 11 or 12 years old, and I'm on the floor,
كان يبلغُ من العمر 11 أو 12 عامًا، وكنتُ على الأرض،
and I'm crying because I saved a lot of money for that bike,
وكنتُ أبكي لأنني وفرتُ الكثير من المال من أجل تلك الدراجة،
and I'm crying and I stand up and I start screaming.
وكنتُ أبكي وثم وقفت على رجليّ وبدأتُ بالصراخ.
Instinct steps in, and I start screaming, "Mwizi, mwizi!"
خطوات غريزية طبيعية قد اتخذتها، وبداتُ أصرخ "مويزي، مويزي!"
which means "thief" in Swahili.
والتي تعني "لص" باللغة السواحلية.
And out of the woodworks, all of these people come out
ومن بين تلك الأشجار، خرج جميع الناس
and they start to give chase.
وبدأوا في ملاحقة اللص.
This is Africa, so mob justice in action.
هذه هي أفريقيا، لذلك فالعدالة الغوعائية تعمل.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
And I round the corner, and they've captured him,
وكنتُ أدورُ حول الزاوية، وقاموا بالقبض عليه،
they've caught him.
قاموا بإمساكه.
The suspect has been apprehended,
تم القبض على المشبوه به،
and they make him give me my bike back,
وأرغموه على إرجاع دراجتي لي،
and they also make him apologize.
وأرغموه أيضًا على الاعتذار لي.
Again, you know, typical African justice, right?
مرةً أخرى، وكما تعلمون، العدالة الإفريقية المثالية، اليس كذلك؟
And so they make him say sorry.
وأجبروه أن يتأسف لي.
And so we stand there facing each other,
ووقفنا هناك في مواجهة بعضنا البعض،
and he looks at me, and he says sorry,
ونظر لي وقال: آسف،
but he looks at me with this unbridled fury.
ولكنه نظر لي بغضبٍ جامح.
He is very, very angry.
كان غاضبًا جدًا جدًا،
And it is the first time that I have been confronted with someone
وكانت المرة الأولى التي أواجه فيها شخصًا
who doesn't like me simply because of what I represent.
لا يحبني ببساطة بسبب ما أمثله.
He looks at me with this look as if to say,
نظر لي تلك النظرة وكأنه يقول،
"You, with your shiny skin and your bike, you're angry at me?"
"أنتِ ببشرتك اللامعة ودراجتك، أنت غاضبة مني!"
So it was a hard lesson that he didn't like me,
وهكذا، كان الدرس قاسيًا بأنه لا يحبني،
but you know what, he was right.
لكن كما تعلمون، كان على حق.
I was a middle-class kid living in a poor country.
كنت طفلة أنتمي إلى الطبقة المتوسطة التي تعيشُ في بلدٍ فقير.
I had a bike, and he barely had food.
كان لديّ دراجة، وكان لديه بالكاد الطعام.
Sometimes, it's the messages that we don't want to hear,
أحيانًا، إنها الرسالة التي لا نرغبُ في سماعها،
the ones that make us want to crawl out of ourselves,
تلك التي تجعلنا نريدُ الزحف والخروج من أنفسنا،
that we need to hear the most.
وأننا نحتاج إلى سماع المزيد.
For every lovable storyteller who steals your heart,
من كل روائي محبوب الذي يسرقُ ويأسرُ قلوبكم،
there are hundreds more whose voices are slurred and ragged,
هناك المئات من الذين أصواتهم خشنة وملابسهم رثة،
who don't get to stand up on a stage dressed in fine clothes like this.
الذين لا يستطيعون الوقوف على المسرح وارتداء ملابس جميلة مثل هذه.
There are a million angry-boy-on-a-bike stories
هناك مليون طفل مثل طفل الدراجة الغاضب
and we can't afford to ignore them
ولا نستطيع تجاهلهم
simply because we don't like their protagonists
لأنه وببساطة لا نحب أنصارهم
or because that's not the kid that we would bring home with us
أو بسبب أنه ليس الطفل الذي نرغبُ في إحضاره للمنزل معنا
from the orphanage.
من دار الأيتام.
The third reason that I think
أعتقد أن السبب الثالث
that stories don't necessarily make the world a better place
بأنه ليس بالضرورة أن تجعل القصص العالم أفضل مكانًا
is that too often we are so invested in the personal narrative
هو لأننا في الغالب نستثمر وقتنا في السرد الشخصي
that we forget to look at the bigger picture.
وننسى أن ننظر في الصورة الأكبر.
And so we applaud someone
ونهتفُ لشخصٍ ما
when they tell us about their feelings of shame,
عندما يخبرنا حول شعوره بالعار،
but we don't necessarily link that to oppression.
ولكن لا نربط ذلك بالضرورة بالظلم.
We nod understandingly when someone says they felt small,
نومىء بأننا فهمنا عندما يشعرُ أحدهم بأنه غير مهم،
but we don't link that to discrimination.
ولكن لا نربط ذلك بالتمييز.
The most important stories, especially for social justice,
أكثر القصص أهمية خاصةً بالنسبة إلى العدالة الاجتماعية،
are those that do both,
هي تلك القصص التي تقوم بالدورين،
that are both personal and allow us to explore and understand the political.
التي هي شخصية وتسمحُ لنا في اكتشاف وفهم السياسة.
But it's not just about the stories we like
لكنها ليست حول القصص التي نحب فقط
versus the stories we choose to ignore.
مقابل القصص الني نختارُ تجاهلها.
Increasingly, we are living in a society where there are larger forces at play,
على نحوٍ متزايد، نحنُ نعيش في مجتمعٍ حيثُ هناك قوى أكبر في الساحة،
where stories are actually for many people beginning to replace the news.
حيث بدأت القصص في الحقيقة تحلُ محل الأخبار بالنسبة إلى العديد من الناس.
Yeah?
نعم!
We live in a time where we are witnessing the decline of facts,
نعيش في زمنٍ حيث نشهدُ رفض الحقائق،
when emotions rule
عندما تحكمُ العواطف
and analysis, it's kind of boring, right?
والتحليلات، إنها مملة نوعًا ما، أليس كذلك؟
Where we value what we feel more than what we actually know.
حيثُ نثمنُ ما نشعرُ به أكثر مما نعرفه في الواقع.
A recent report by the Pew Center on trends in America
هناك تقرير حديث من قبل "مركز بيو" عن الاتجاهات في أمريكا
indicates that only 10 percent of young adults under the age of 30
يشيرُ إلى أن 10% فقط من الشباب تحت سن الثلاثين
"place a lot of trust in the media."
"يضعون الكثير من ثقتهم في وسائل الاعلام."
Now, this is significant.
الآن، هذا الأمر مهم جدًا.
It means that storytellers are gaining trust
وهو ما يعني أن رواة القصص ينالون الثقة
at precisely the same moment
في نفس الوقت تمامًا
that many in the media are losing the confidence in the public.
الذي يفقدُ فيه العديد في وسائل الاعلام الثقة من عامة الناس.
This is not a good thing,
وهذا الشيء ليس جيدًا،
because while stories are important
لأنه بينما القصص هي مهمة
and they help us to have insights in many ways,
وتساعدنا في تكوين رؤى في مجالات كثيرة،
we need the media.
نحنُ بحاجة إلى وسائل الإعلام.
From my years as a social justice activist,
كناشطة عدالة اجتماعية لسنوات عديدة
I know very well that we need credible facts from media institutions
أعرفُ جيدًا أننا نحتاجُ إلى حقائق موثوقة من المؤسسات الإعلامية
combined with the powerful voices of storytellers.
بجانب الأصوات الفعالة من رواة القصص.
That's what pushes the needle forward in terms of social justice.
وهذا ما يدفعُ النشاط قدمًا فيما يخص العدالة الاجتماعية.
In the final analysis, of course,
في التحليل النهائي، بالطبع،
it is justice
إنها العدالة
that makes the world a better place,
التي تجعلُ العالم مكانًا أفضل،
not stories. Right?
وليس القصص، أليس كذلك؟
And so if it is justice that we are after,
ولذلك، إذا كانت العدالة هي ما نبحثُ عنها،
then I think we mustn't focus on the media or on storytellers.
فأعتقد أنه لا ينبغي علينا التركيز على وسائل الاعلام أو رواة القصص.
We must focus on audiences,
علينا التركيز على الجماهير،
on anyone who has ever turned on a radio
على كل شخص يستمعُ إلى الإذاعة
or listened to a podcast,
أو يستمعُ إلى البث الحي،
and that means all of us.
وهذا يعني جميعنا.
So a few concluding thoughts
لذلك، إليكم بعض الأفكار الختامية
on what audiences can do to make the world a better place.
حول ما يستطيع الجماهير عمله لجعل العالم أفضل مكانًا.
So firstly, the world would be a better place, I think,
أولاً، أعتقدُ ان العالم سيكون مكانًا أفضل
if audiences were more curious and more skeptical
إذا أصبحت الجماهير أكثر فضولًا وأكثر ريبةً
and asked more questions about the social context
وتطرحُ المزيد من الأسئلة حول سياق العدالة
that created those stories that they love so much.
التي تنتجُ تلك القصص التي يحبونها كثيرًا.
Secondly, the world would be a better place
ثانيًا، سيكون العالم مكانًا أفضل
if audiences recognized that storytelling is intellectual work.
إذا أدركت الجماهير بأن رواية القصص هي عمل فكري ثقافي.
And I think it would be important for audiences
وأعتقدُ أنه من المهم بالنسبة إلى الجماهير
to demand more buttons on their favorite websites,
المطالبة بمزيد من الأزرار على المواقع الإلكترونية المفضلة لديهم.
buttons for example that say,
أزرار تقول على سبيل المثال،
"If you liked this story,
"إذا أحببتم هذه القصة،
click here to support a cause your storyteller believes in."
انقروا هنا لدعم قضية يؤمن بها الروائي المفضل لديكم.
Or "click here to contribute to your storyteller's next big idea."
أو، "انقروا هنا للمساهمة بالفكرة القادمة للروائي المفضل لديكم."
Often, we are committed to the platforms,
في معظم الأحيان، نحن نلتزم بالمنصات،
but not necessarily to the storytellers themselves.
وليس بالضرورة للروائيين أنفسهم.
And then lastly, I think that audiences can make the world a better place
وأخيرًا، أعتقد أنه بإمكان الجماهير جعل العالم أفضل
by switching off their phones,
عن طريق إغلاق هواتفهم،
by stepping away from their screens
والابتعاد عن شاشاتهم،
and stepping out into the real world beyond what feels safe.
والخروج إلى العالم الحقيقي إلى ما وراء الشعور بالأمن.
Alice Walker has said,
قالت "أليس ووكر"،
"Look closely at the present you are constructing.
"انظروا للحاضر الذي تشيدونه عن كثب،
It should look like the future you are dreaming."
يجبُ أن يبدو مثل المستقبل الذي تحلمون به."
Storytellers can help us to dream,
يستطيع رواة القصص جعلنا نحلم،
but it's up to all of us to have a plan for justice.
ولكن يعود كل شيء لنا ليكون لدينا خطة لتحقيق العدالة الإجتماعية.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)